<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To His Grace William, Duke of Hamilton Their Majesties High Commissioner and the Honourable Estates of Parliament, humblt sheweth the answers for Hendry Navilpayne, to the inditement raised at the instance of Their Majesties advocate, before the high court of Parliament.</title>
            <author>Payne, Henry Neville, fl. 1672-1710.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1693</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 29 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 4 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91535</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P893A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R181560</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45097887</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45097887</idno>
            <idno type="VID">171466</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91535)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 171466)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2575:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>To His Grace William, Duke of Hamilton Their Majesties High Commissioner and the Honourable Estates of Parliament, humblt sheweth the answers for Hendry Navilpayne, to the inditement raised at the instance of Their Majesties advocate, before the high court of Parliament.</title>
                  <author>Payne, Henry Neville, fl. 1672-1710.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>4 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the John Carter Brown Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Payne, Henry Neville, fl. 1672-1710 --  Trials, litigation, etc.</term>
               <term>Hamilton, William Douglas, --  Duke of, 1635-1694.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1689-1702.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>Graham Hukill</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="modern_bookplate">
            <pb facs="tcp:171466:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Copied from the original in the John Carter Brown Library</p>
            <figure>
               <q>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>DAD</q>
               <head>John Carter Brown Lihrary Brown University</head>
            </figure>
            <p>Not to be reproduced with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out permission.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:171466:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:171466:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO HIS GRACE WILLIAM DUKE of HAMILTON THEIR MAJESTIES HIGH COMMISSIONER And the Honourable ESTATES of PARLIAMENT, <hi>H<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>MBLT SHEWETH THE</hi> Anſwers for <hi>Hendry Navilpayne,</hi> To the Indite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment raiſed at the Inſtance of Their Majeſties Advocate, before the High Court of Parliament.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hereas it is Lybelled in the ſaid Inditement, That the Defender did come here to <hi>Scotland</hi> for purſhewing Treaſonable practiſes, againſt the Government; And that being thereupon apprehended &amp; Impriſoned. he hath hitherto proſecute the ſaid deſign by keeping Correſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pondence with diſſafected Perſons and Enemies to Their Majeſties Government, &amp; did openly declare, that there was an Invaſion deſigned both Here &amp; in <hi>England,</hi> and that the Defender did carry on the ſame under diſguieſed names, both for Perſons and Things; And that his ſaid Project is already found, and declared by a vote of Parliament, paſt upon a letter alleaged written by the Defender, daited the <hi>3d:</hi> of <hi>December</hi> 1692: And which letter is <hi>verbatim</hi> contained in the ſaid Inditement, and a Commentar or Expoſition put thereupon by my Lord Advocate; And pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending, That there are ſeveral other letters written, and ſubſcribed by the Defender, by which his hand write, and guilt of the premiſſes will evidently appear.</p>
            <p>It is Anſwered for the Defender, That, He is exceedingly ſurpriſed to ſee ſuch an Inditement preſented againſt him, And, the raither, That being a Stranger, and abſolutely ignorant of the Laws and Cuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toms of this Kingdom, He ſhould have received an Inditement upon Thurſday laſt, to Compear and Anſwer this day, And ſo, not having ſix free dayes! And Lawyers having refuſed to give him Advice before they were Authoriſed by their Majeſties Commiſſioner, and the Eſtates of Parliament, to do the ſame. It is impoſſible for the Defender, to have all theſe Evidences read in ſo ſhort a time, which he would have adduced for Vindication of his own innocencie, anent all that is lybelled againſt him, in caſe he had been charged upon fifteen free dayes, as (conform as the Defender is informed) is uſual to be practiſed in the like caſes, Eſpecially where the Defender was for ſo long time a cloſs priſoner, and ſo precluded from having the Advice or converſe of any perſon, whereby he might have been aſſiſted to prepare himſelf for this Tryal; And therefore, He humbly beggs, and expects, from the High and Honourable Court of Parliament, That they will be pleaſed to allow him ſome further time to have his Defenceſs and inſtructions thereof, in readineſs againſt this inditement.</p>
            <p>But leaſt it ſhould be pretended, That the Defender were inclyned to ſhift and tergiverſe in this Affair. Albeit he hath not all the proofs and Evidence of his innocence here in readineſs, which otherwiſe he could have adduced, in caſe a competent time had been allowed him; Yet for convincing their Majeſtie High Commiſſioner, and the Honourable Eſtates of Parliament (as far as is poſſible upon ſuch a ſur<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>prize) of the Defenders innocence, He doth abſolutely deny the Inditement, and whole Members Qua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lifications, Circumſtances, and Aggravations therein contained; And as to that point of the lybel anen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Defender his coming to <hi>Scotland,</hi> out of a treaſonable deſign, denying, as ſaid is, It is repreſented fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> him; That as he hopes it is well known to ſeveral Honourable Members of Parliament, That the panna<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> upon his firſt entring within the Kingdom, was apprehended without any warrand from Authority, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a number of Countrey People, who were occaſionally convocate together for the time, And brought i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> where he was immediately impriſoned, and in which place, and in <hi>Stirling</hi> and <hi>Blackneſs,</hi> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> hath continued now priſoner for the ſpace of more then three years; And for more then two of theſe yea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> a cloſs Priſoner: And the true deſign of the Pannals coming for <hi>Scotland</hi> was that he being a <hi>Roman Cath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick,</hi> And apprehenſive, that thoſe of his perſwaſion might meet with ſome ſeverities in <hi>England:</hi> A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:171466:3"/>having ſent ſome of his Effects abroad, he did reſolve to have gone off the Kingdom, and lived privately; But there being an Embargo then put upon all the Ships in <hi>England,</hi> ſo that he could get no occaſion for going abroad at any Harbour there; He came for <hi>Scotland</hi> out of a harmleſs deſign, to get the occaſion of ſhipping here; And which is evident and undenyable, and clear from this, That there was not found in his Cuſtody, when he was firſt apprehended, any Papers relating to the Government any manner of way, and the only Paper then found upon him, being a Catalogue of the initial letters of five mens names, with two Letters ſubjoyned to each of theſe two Initial Letters, he did before the Lords of Privy Council, when he was under Tortour, Freely and Candidly expone theſe Initial Letters, and deſignations thereto ſubjoyned, by declaring that J: G: L: S: was underſtood. <hi>John Gilles</hi> Skiper in <hi>Leith,</hi> where the Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal was intended to have come and ſtayed until he had got occaſion of Shipping abroad, and that the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther two to which the two letters M. A. were ſubjoyned, were Merchants at <hi>Amſterdam:</hi> And the laſt two to which the letters B: P: were ſubjoyned, were Bankers at <hi>Paris,</hi> with whom the Pannall had ſetled ſome of his Effects: And the pannal did then condeſcend upon the names and ſurnames of the ſaid four per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, And that there were then ſuch perſons in <hi>Amſterdam</hi> and <hi>Paris,</hi> as the pannal did then condeſcend upon: Neither then was, nor as yet can be contraverted, ſo that the pannal admires that their Majeſties Advocate ſhould as a preface to this inditement, alleadge that the pannals coming to <hi>Scotland,</hi> was out of a Treaſonable deſign, thereby to repreſent him as unfavourable to the Members of the High and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Court of Parliament, He being a Stranger to this Kingdom, and abſolutely innocent thereof, as is above repreſented: And that their Majeſties Advocate ſhould farder inſinuate, that the pannal during his impriſonment ſhould have been tampering with Enemies, for diſturbing of the Government, and peace of the Kingdom: It being clear and obvious, That a priſoner, eſpecially a cloſs priſoner, to whom paper, pen, and ink, and acceſs from all other perſons were diſcharged, could not be in any poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible capacity, for managing or carrying on any ſuch contrivances or deſignes: And albeit the pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal his long and tedious impriſonment, and what he ſuffered while he was priſoner, could not but be grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous to any Mortal: Yet he patiently endured the ſame, with that juſt ſubmiſſion, and humble ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieſcence that is due to Authority; And therefore he humbly conceives, that Charity it ſelf will vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate a poor Stranger from any ſuch imputation, And that he needs not make uſe of any other legal Argument for his Vindication thereof, And in Caſe the Pannal were Conſcious to himſelf of any ſuch Guilt or Deſign, as truely he is not; Yet he hath this Unanſwerable Defence in Law, That having en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured Tortur two ſeveral times, and being Interrogat upon the Occaſion, and his deſign of his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for <hi>Scotland</hi> whilſt he was under the Tortut, And having denyed any other Deſign, then as is above-repreſented, <hi>viz:</hi> to go abroad, and live privately, he cannot now be Indited or purſued upon that account, conform to the Law and Cuſtome of all Nations.</p>
            <p>And as to that part of the Inditement, bearing that the Pannal did frequently declare that there was an Invaſion deſigned, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> It is Anſwered, that denying the ſame, yet the Common Diſcourſe of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, being theſe two years by paſt, that there was an Invaſion deſigned from <hi>France</hi> into <hi>Brittain:</hi> The Pannal his repeating the Common and ordinary Diſcourſe of the Countrey; And which was contained in ſeveral publick News Letters, can never be ſtretched to make him lyable to the Crimes and Pains libelled. <hi>2do.</hi> The Pannal not being a <hi>Scots</hi> Subject, and never having received any Benefite or Protection from the Government in <hi>Scotland:</hi> But being an <hi>Engliſhman,</hi> and there being more free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Liberty of Speech allowed in <hi>England,</hi> than is permitted by the Law of <hi>Scotland,</hi> albeit any Raſh Expreſſions had eſcaped the Pannal (and which he abſolutely denyes) yet he could only be Tryed and Puniſhed therefore, conform to the Laws of his Native Countrey of <hi>England,</hi> by whoſe Laws &amp; Cuſtomes He was obliedged to Walke and Conform his Life and Deportment into, and not conform to the Laws of <hi>Scotland,</hi> whereof he was no Subject; And which he neither knew, nor was preſumed or obliedged to know. <hi>3tio.</hi> The Pannal being Naturally Melancholy, and His Melancholy being much augmented and increaſed by His long Impriſonment &amp; Sufferings. It is offered to be proven, that during all the time of His Impriſonment, His Converſation &amp; Diſcourſe was Harmeleſs &amp; Innocent, &amp; Free &amp; Open, as is Natural to all <hi>Engliſhmen:</hi> So that in Charity (if any Diſcourſe hath eſcaped Him) The ſame ought to be Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, as deſigned only to ſuport himſelf againſt the Grouth and Increaſe of his Melancholy, eſpecially ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it cannot be made appear, that in his Diſcourſes he did Tamper with any Perſon, But on the contrair, that he uſed that ſame freedom of Diſcourſe with all concerned in the Government and Authority, with whom he had Occaſion to Converſe, which he did Utter and Expreſs to any other perſon whatſomever. And it is not conceiveable how ſuch Diſcourſes can be ſtretched to inferr any Plot or Contriveance by the Pannal, when the ſame was publickly Talked and uttered by him, to thoſe who were concerned in the Government.</p>
            <p>And as to that part of the Libel, mentioning an Vote or Opinion of Parliament; The Pannal humbly conceives, that he himſelf cannot at all be Obliedged to make any anſwer thereto, there being no ſuch Vote or Opinion of Parliament, or Double thereof, given to him with his Inditement. <hi>2do.</hi> Neither (as the Pannal humbly conceives) can he any wayes be concerned therein, as to this Inditement preſented againſt him: Becauſe albeit the leaſt ſuſpiſion may give the Government occaſion to ſecure the Kingdom againſt Plots and Miſcheaſs, yet where there is no Vote or Act of Parliament, fixing the guilt againſt the <hi>Pannal Nominatum,</hi> He can never be precluded from any Competent defence for ſecuring of his Life, by any ſuch Vote to the paſſing whereof the <hi>Pannal</hi> was not called.</p>
            <p>And as to the laſt &amp; matterial part of the Indytement, founded upon a miſſive Letter alleadged wirt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by the <hi>Pannal:</hi> And the Commentar and expoſition thereof contained in the inditement, and my Lord Advocat, his offering to prove the ſame to be the <hi>Pannals</hi> hand Write; <hi>Comperatione literarum,</hi> and by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther papers and miſſive Letters under the <hi>Pannals</hi> own hand, ready to be produced.</p>
            <p>It is Anſwered, that the <hi>Pannal</hi> doth abſolutly deny that ever he Wrote any Letter of the Tenor, and Contents Libelled, and the ſaid Principal Letter ought to have been produced and ſhewn to the <hi>Pannal</hi> himſelf. And he allowed to conſider the ſame before he can be obliedged to make any Anſwer thereto. <hi>2do.</hi> By the double of the ſaid pretended Letter, as it is ſet down at the end of the Coppy of the Inditement given to the <hi>Pannea;</hi> The ſame appears neither to be ſubſcrived by the <hi>Pannal,</hi> nor to be derected for any perſon whatſomever; So that it is obvious to common ſence, that the ſaid Pretended Letter hath been allennatly the product of the ſame diſtempered and Melancholly brain. <hi>3tio.</hi> It is not at all Libelled, that ever this pretended Letter was ſent abroad, or delivered to any Perſon whatſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:171466:3"/>nor doth the inditement condeſcend upon any perſon, by whome the ſame was conveyed away, nor in whoſe Cuſtody the ſaid pretended Letter was found, without all which, were ſpecially Libelled and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed: The Inditement can never be found Relevant, to ſuſtain this Criminal Libel and concluſion againſt the <hi>Pannal</hi> becauſe in caſe ſuch a ſpecial Condeſcendance were made; The <hi>Pannal</hi> would exculpate himſelf by referring to, and proving by theſe perſons Oaths, that the ſaid pretended Letter had been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed and delivered to them by ſome other perſon than the <hi>Pannal;</hi> and that the ſame was the hand write of ſome other perſon than the <hi>Pannal,</hi> and that the Tenor, and import thereof was abſolutly differ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ant from, and inconſiſtant with the expoſition and Commentar, put thereupon, by my Lord Advocate. <hi>4to.</hi> Albeit a perſon in a Melancholly or diſtemper, ſhould Scrible over a rediculous and impertinent paper for the eaſe of his diſturbed fancie for the time, yet in caſe he ſhould either before he ſubſcrived the ſame, and before he directed it to any perſon cancel the ſaid impertinent and rediculous paper, or let the ſame fall by as neglected ſuch a paper; albeit thereafter found in the Cuſtody of the Melancholly Perſon or in his Room, would never make the ſaid Melancholly perſon lyable to the Crimes and pains libelled, unleſs he had diſperſed and ſent the ſame abroad, becauſe <hi>hoc ipſo,</hi> that he never made uſe thereof, by directing the ſame to any perſon. Law preſumes that he paſſed from, and repented of that which the diſtempered fitt of his melancholly had formerly prompted him to.</p>
            <p>And as to that part of the inditement, bearing that my Lord Advocat Intends to prove <hi>Comparatione Literarum,</hi> that the ſaid pretended miſſive Letter is the <hi>Pannals</hi> hand write. It is anſwered, <hi>1mo.</hi> That ſeeing the Pannal abſolutely denys the ſame to be his handwrite, or that he had acceſſion thereto, or knows any thing of the deſigne thereof in the leaſt, yet he humbly repreſents to my Lord Commiſſioners his Grace, and the Honourable Eſtates of Parliament, that it is an uncontraverted printiple in Law, that as every man is preſumed to be innocent and free from all guilt and fine, until the contrair thereof be inſtructed againſt him by a clear probation; So by the Laws and Cuſtomes of all Nations, and by the opinion of all Doctors that ever wrote upon the Criminal Law; This is uncontraverted and undenyable, that the guilt of any Crime, by which a Capital concluſion for taking away a mans life may be inferred, can be fixed upon any perſon, except by a poſitive probation, as clear as the Sun ſhininng in his Meridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an: And neither the Law nor Cuſtome of any Nation did ever allow Capital Crimes to be proven by conjectures or preſumptions: And GOD Almighty himſelf by the mouth of <hi>Moſes,</hi> requires two or three witneſſes in all ſuch caſſes: So that for my Lord Advocat to pretend to have a preſumptive or conjectural probation ſuſtained to him againſt the <hi>Pannal,</hi> who is a poor ſtranger, for taking away of his Life, is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Law and practiſe of this, and all other Nations. <hi>2do.</hi> Albeit <hi>Comparatio Literarum</hi> and or her papers have been ſuſtained to Adminiculat a write, and to make up the defects of the ſolemnities thereof, yet no inſtance can be given, where ever ſuch a probation was ſuſtained Relevant, to fix a Capital guilt upon any perſon, to take away his Life. <hi>3tio.</hi> As all probation, eſpecially in caſſes capitally Criminal, ought to be clear as the Sun, and poſitive, and pregnat, and incapable of any doubiety, or uncertainty: So it is referred to my Lord Commiſſioner, his Grace, and the Honourable E. ſtates of Parliament, whither a probation by compariſon of Letters, and hand-writes, can be ſo pregnant, clear, and certain, that it is abſolutely incapable of being redargued by other docu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, or whither or not the ſame be in all caſſes ſubject to doubtfulneſs and uncertainty, ſeeing the moſt that can be inferred from ſuch a probation is, That the hand Write are like to other, and (as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, is not the ſame) So it is certain that many hand writes are like to others; And it is notterly known, and offered to be proven, That ſome perſons have attained to that perfection of Writing, that they are able to counterfeit whole ſheets of paper, as Writen by any other perſon, to that exactneſs and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, that the perſon himſelf whoſe hand Write is fienzied and counterfeited, can ſcarcely be able to deny the ſame, to be his own hand Write; And ſeing a deciſion in Parliament, in this caſe will be a Rule &amp; precedent, &amp; have the force of a Law, in all criminal caſes for the Future; It is Referred to the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the High &amp; Honourable Court of Parliament, what the dangerous conſequence of ſuch a prepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, might in proceſs of time amount to, and whither the lives and fortunes of any Subject: Be not at the diſcretion of any ſilly Rogue who hath the skill and villany to counterfeit his hand Write. <hi>4to.</hi> This is alſo an undenyable principle both in Law and Religion, that it is better to let a Thouſand guilty perſons go free, then that the blood of an Innocent perſon ſhould be ſhed, Becauſe, albeit a guilty perſon ſhould eſcape the hand of Juſtice for a time. Almighty GOD might thereafter ſuffer him to fall in an other ſnare; By which he might thereafter be brought to condingue puniſhment for all: And which is not only clear from the inſtances of <hi>Joab</hi> and <hi>Shimei:</hi> But many inſtances thereof might be given in this and our Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour Nations: And the book entituled GODS Reveange againſt Murder, hath many examples thereof; Whereas on the other hand, the ſhedding of the blood of an innocent perſon, is like water ſpilt upon the ground, which cannot be gathered up, or recovered, but lyes as a burden upon the Land; <hi>calling for Vengeance from Heaven:</hi> And this is a common principle received, and conſtantly repeated in the mouths of all Mankind, That the caſe of a Defender, when purſued for his life, is alwayes moſt favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able; And when there is any thing doubtful, either as to the Relevancie or probation which may ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit of a twofold ſenſe or interpretation, The Expoſition and Interpretation Thereof, is alwayes to be made in favours of the pannal, and Defenders: And by the Opinion of all Lawyers, <hi>Jura ſunt cogenda,</hi> That is, the Laws themſelves are to be ſtretched, and even forced ſo far as is poſſible in favours of the pannal, for abſolving him from the crimes lybelled, and preſervation of his blood. <hi>5to.</hi> Neither can my Lord Advocate be allowed to make uſe of any letters for probation againſt the pannall, ſeeing no ſuch letters nor doubles thereof were given out to the pannal, with his inditement, as they ought to have been.</p>
            <p>And as to the Commentar and Expoſition of that pretended letter, whereupon the Inditement is foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed, which my Lord Advocate hath made, <hi>The Pannal not being at all concerned in the Letter, he cannot be concerned <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> what Expoſition or Commentar My Lord Advocat thinks fit, or fancies with himſelf to put upon the ſame:</hi> And albeit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> doth admire the quickneſs of my Lord Advocates Fancie in that commentar; Yet he humbly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ves, that his Fancie and Opinion can never be ſuſtained to infer any crime or guilt againſt the pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> , Becauſe, <hi>1mo.</hi> The whole ſtrain of that Expoſition, being an alleadged Deſign in the Writer; As <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Law can be alleadged for allowing a Deſign, which is only the thought of a Mans breaſt, to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> by Witneſſes, or by other Mens conjectures; So there is no inſtance thereof can be adduced in this <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ny other Nation, <hi>The enquiring into and judging the thoughts of the heart, being the prerogative of GOD Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ty, which He hath reſerved to Himſelf, excluding all Mortals from any ſhare thereof. 2do.</hi> As the deſign and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:171466:4"/>meaning of the Writer of that pretended letter, is neither in Law probable by Witneſſes, nor can the deſign thereof be inferred from preſumptions or conjectures; So it is referred to the Wiſdom of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, Whether or not the ſtretches made by my Lord Advocate in that expoſition, be either pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumable or conſiſtent with themſelves. Becauſe, <hi>1mo.</hi> The lybel tending to inferr the pannal his keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Treaſonable correſpondence with Enemies abroad: My Lord Advocate neither condeſcends upon the perſons names, or deſignation, with whom the ſaid correſpondence is alleadged to have been kept, and without condeſcendance upon the ſame, the Relevancie cannot be ſuſtained. <hi>2do.</hi> Can any Ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Man preſume or imagine, That the late King would take up his meaſures in matters of the greateſt importance, from a perſon of ſo little ſignification and intereſt, and of ſo little conduct, as the pannal is known to be: Eſpecially, conſidering the circumſtances the pannal was in at the time, and for ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral years preceeding, being alwayes a priſoner, and for the moſt part of that time a cloſs priſoner. <hi>3tio.</hi> How can the late King, his late Declaration for <hi>England,</hi> be pretended to be the product and conſequence of this pretended miſſive letter, whereupon the Inditement is founded, as my Lord Advocate expreſly lybels, Seeing it is clear, That the ſaid pretended letter, did never come to the late Kings hands: For, if it had once come to his hands, how is it poſſible that it could now be produced before the Parliament, as a pretended inſtruction of his inditement. And this <hi>per ſe</hi> is ſufficient to demonſtrate to the World, That my Lord Advocates commentar and expoſition of that pretended letter, is only groundleſs and conjectural: And doth redargue the Faith of his Commentars thereupon. <hi>4to.</hi> Whereas it is pretended by my Lord Advocates commentar upon this letter, That the pannal deſired a Gift from the late King of the Clerkſhip of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> in favours of Mr. <hi>Patrick Smith,</hi> or his ſon, upon the account that his Wife had been long impriſoned upon the pannals account; And that the pannal would have been ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved if ſhe had not ſupplied him. It is anſwered, <hi>1mo.</hi> That it is abſolutely denyed, that ever <hi>Mr. Patrick Smiths</hi> Wife was impriſoned upon the pannals account, or that ever ſhe was impriſoned ſince the pannal came to <hi>Scotland:</hi> Neither doth the pannal know if ſhe be fled or not, or upon what account. And Mr. <hi>Patrick Smith</hi> is known to be in that circumſtances, that he is even much ſtraitned as to the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainance of himſelf and his family. <hi>2do.</hi> Could the pannal be pretended to be ſo ridiculous, (unleſs he had been under ſome melancholly diſtemper,) to write for the Gift of a Clerkſhip, where there was no Vaccancie, <hi>Eneas Mackleod</hi> being then in poſſeſſion of the equal half of the place, long before Sir <hi>James Rocheads</hi> deceaſs, And being ſecured in the ſurvivancie of the other half many years before: And that Clerkſhip being known to be not at the Kings diſpoſal, but only at the diſpoſal of the Town Council, when vaccant. And to clear the High Court of Parliament, That this is only a deſigned ſtretch, for loading of the pannal, when the debates were betwixt the Old and New Councils of <hi>Edinburgh,</hi> anent their Elections: There was an other perſon then ſpecially condeſeended upon, as deſigned for that Clerkſhip.</p>
            <p>And as to that pretence, That in the ſaid Letter by the word (Agents) is underſtood; My Lord Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocat, and Lord Juſtice Clerk, in reſpect they were nominate to theſe Imployments by the King, about four dayes before the date of that pret ended Letter, <hi>viz:</hi> upon the 28 of <hi>November;</hi> And this pretended Letter, is alleadged to be dated the third of <hi>December</hi> thereafter. It is anſwered, that ſeeing it is impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, that what was done at <hi>London</hi> upon the 28 of <hi>November,</hi> could have come to the Pannals Knowledge, who was then a priſoner at <hi>Blackneſs</hi> in ſo few dayes, in that Seaſon of the year: This doth convincingly redargue that part of my Lord Advocates Commentar; And the pannal is content to depone, <hi>That he never knew or heard of my Lord Juſtice Clerk his being preferred untill he did ſee his Lordſhip, latelie in the Toolbooth of Edinburgh. And, That he never heard of my Lord Advocates preferment, untill long after the date of that pretended letter.</hi> And therefore it is referred to the Juſtice and Wiſdom of the High Court of parliament, Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther or not ſuch uncertain conjectures, as to all the Branches of my Lord Advocates Commentar and Expoſition of that letter, evidently appears to be, Can by the Law of this or any other Kingdom be ſuſtained, as is a clear and convincing probation to fix a Criminal Guilt upon a poor Stranger to take away his Life! And as the ſaid Letter appears to be the nonſenſical product of a diſturbed Brain in all the points thereof; So there is neither any thing lybelled or produced, which can inſtruct any one of the Names or Particulars therein contained to be the ſame, which My Lord Advocat affirms and ſuppoſes in his Expoſition.</p>
            <p>And ſeeing by the Claime of Right of this Kingdom, (and which the Petitioner humbly conceives to be equivolent to the Petition of Right in <hi>England,</hi> the great and unqueſtionable Securitys of the Subjects of his Native Kingdom.) It is expreſly declared, that the purſuing perſons, upon ſtretches from old and Obſolet Laws or upon Frivolous and Weak Pretences, or Lame and Defective Probation, are contrair to Law, and that there was never a Criminal Libel offered to be founded upon ſuch Weak and Frivolous Pretences as this; The foundation thereof, being only a pretended Miſſive Letter, neither ſubſcrived nor directed nor delivered to any perſon; But as it appears to be the Melancholy Product of a diſturbed Brain. So alſo it appears to have been caſually loſt and neglected, and as there can neither Senſe not Crime be inferred from the Letter it ſelf; So all that is libelled againſt the Pannal, as Criminal there-from, is only founded upon My Lord Advocats own Fanſie and Conjecture, So the Probation offered there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, <hi>Viz. Comparatio Literarum,</hi> being ſuch as never was yet ſuſtained in any Court, for taking away the Life of a Man; The Pannal humbly conceives, that this Libel and Probation offered againſt him, by the foreſaid Clauſe in the Claime of Right, is expreſly declared to be contrair to Law. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, albeit the Pannal be a poor Stranger, and that he be alſo unknown to the Members of this Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Court of Parliament, as he is ignorant of the Laws of this Kingdom: Yet ſeeing it is his Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortune (and for which he is heartily ſorry) to be indited and accuſed of ſuch high and Attrocious Crimes. He judges himſelf happy in this, that he is to be tryed before My Lord Commiſſioner, his Grace, and the Honourable Eſtates of Parliament, of whoſe impartial Juſtice to a poor Stranger now purſued for his Life, he is not in the leaſt doubtfull, but on the Contrair out of the Conſciouſneſs of his own In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence, doth repoſe an entire Confidence in their impartial Juſtice, And humbly expects therefrom to be aſſoilȝied from his groundleſs lybel, which contrair to the claime of Right, is only founded upon frivolous and weak pretences, and craved to be ſupported and made out by a Lame and Defective Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation in manner Above repreſented.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:171466:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
